Guide to the George and Anna Hamlin papers
New York Public Library
George and Anna Hamlin papers
1868-1983
1882-1923
JPB 87-34
22301
Hamlin, George, 1869-1923
New York Public Library Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street New York, NY 10018-2788
3.86 linear feet 10 boxes
George Hamlin (1868-1923) was an American tenor. His daughter, Anna (1900-1988), was a soprano and voice instructor. The George and Anna Hamlin papers, dating from 1868 to 1983, document the careers of both vocalists through clippings, diaries, autograph books, programs, publicity materials, scores, photographs, and correspondence.
George Hamlin (1868-1923) was an American tenor. A student of George Henschel, he toured Europe (1904-1905), and sang with the Chicago Grand Opera Company (1911-1917), but achieved renown for his work as an oratorio and lieder singer. Hamlin was particularly known for his advocacy of the songs of Richard Strauss. His daughter Anna (1900-1988), a soprano, studied with Marcella Sembrich and sang minor roles with the Chicago Civic Opera. She later taught voice at Smith College (1939-1959), and subsequently established a successful vocal studio where her students included Judith Raskin. In 1978, she published Father Was A Tenor (Exposition Press), a memoir.
Anna Hamlin inherited her father's papers and added her own to the collection.
The George and Anna Hamlin papers, dating from 1868 to 1983, document the careers of both vocalists through clippings, diaries, autograph books, programs, publicity materials, scores, photographs, and correspondence. The papers are in two sections, one for George Hamlin and the other for Anna Hamlin.
The George Hamlin papers primarily hold clippings, dating from 1894 to 1941, and programs, which date from 1885 to 1922. They also include photographs, two autograph books, a diary, publicity materials, scores and correspondence.
The photographs consist of two albums of images of family, friends, and colleagues (1909-1917); and loose photographs, some signed, of Hamlin, Ethel Leginksa, Siegfried Ochs, Horatio Parker, Ludwig Wüllner, David Bispham, Clarence Whitehill, Walter Morse Rummell, and Amy Beach (1904-1911). The photographs also contain a caricature of Hamlin in performance. The autograph books, dating from 1882 to 1883, contain signatures of opera stars of the day. The diary documents Hamlin's European tour of 1904 and 1905. Publicity flyers and season brochures date from 1894 to 1908.
Hamlin's papers also contain photographs and papers covering his time at Exeter Academy (1888), and published scores signed by the composers or performers Hamlin worked with (1894-1918). Some scores have Hamlin's annotations. The scores include signatures of or notes from Richard Strauss, Edward Elgar, Victor Herbert, Louis Campbell-Tipton, Walter Morse Rummel, and Yvette Guilbert.
There is a small set of correspondence in George Hamlin's papers dating from 1868 to 1921. It holds letters from Hannibal Hamlin (the Vice President of the United States under Abraham Lincoln), who may have been a relative of George Hamlin, and a letter from Freeman H. Morse to Hannibal Hamlin. These letters concern matters in Maine, for which Hannibal Hamlin served as United States representative, senator, and governor prior to his election as Vice President.
The Anna Hamlin papers include nine diaries, dating from 1912 to 1922; concert programs and correspondence dating from 1915 to 1983; correspondence regarding her book Father Was A Tenor, including a typescript (1978); and clippings (1928-1936).
The collection is divided into sections for George Hamlin and Anna Hamlin.
Donated by Anna Hamlin, 1985-1988.
Collection is open to the public. Library policy on photography and photocopying will apply. Advance notice may be required.
on photocopying and photography will apply.
Beach, H. H. A., Mrs., 1867-1944; Bispham, David Scull, 1857-1921; Campbell-Tipton, Louis, 1877-1921; Elgar, Edward, 1857-1934; Guilbert, Yvette, 1865-1944; Hamlin, Anna M.; Hamlin, Anna M. -- Father was a tenor; Hamlin, Hannibal, 1809-1891; Herbert, Victor, 1859-1924; Leginska, Ethel; Morse, Freeman H. (Freeman Harlow), 1807-1891; Ochs, Siegfried; Parker, Horatio W. (Horatio William), 1863-1919; Rummel, Walter Morse, 1887-1953; Strauss, Richard, 1864-1949; Whitehill, Clarence, 1871-1932; Wüllner, Ludwig; Chicago Grand Opera Company (Chicago, Ill.); Phillips Exeter Academy; Autograph albums; Black-and-white photographs; Brochures; Clippings (information artifacts); Commercial correspondence; Diaries; Fliers (printed matter); Personal correspondence; Programs (documents); Scores; Typescripts; Musicians; Singers
- Hamlin, Anna, 364185
  - Clippings, 1929-1936; 364187; 33433108807284 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diaries, 1914-1922; 364191; 33433108807284 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Father Was A Tenor, 1978; 364193; 33433108807284 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Programs and Correspondence, 1925-1983; 364194; 33433108807292 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Hamlin, George, 364204
  - Autograph Books, 1882-1883; 364205; 33433108807292 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 364209
    - 1894-1903, 364210; 33433108807300 (Box 3, Folder 5-16)
    - 1904-1910, 364211; 33433108807318 (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
    - 1911-1941, 364212; 33433108807326 (Box 5, Folder 1-14)
    - 1915-1917, 364213; 33433108807292 (Box 2, 3)
  - Correspondence, 1868-1921; 364214; 33433108807300 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1904-1905; 364215; 33433108807292 (Box 2, 4)
  - Exeter Academy, 1888; 364216; 33433108807300 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Photographs, 364263
    - Albums, 1909-1911; 1917; undated; 364264; 33433108823208 (Box 9)
    - Caricature, undated; 364265; 33433108823208 (Box 9)
    - Loose Prints, 1904-1911; undated; 364266; 33433108807292 (Box 2, 5-8)
  - Programs, 364267
    - 1885-1901, 364268; 33433108807334 (Box 6, Folder 1-11)
    - 1902-1907, 364269; 33433108807342 (Box 7, Folder 1-10)
    - 1908-1922, 364270; 33433108807359 (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
  - Publicity, 1894-1908; 364272; 33433108807300 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Scores, 1894-1918; 364271; 33433108823216 (Box 10, Folder 1-8)